[Music]
over a century ago fasting was hailed
not only as a means of competing
cerebral latitude but also for the
prolongation of healthy longevity
if that turns out to be true fgf21 might
be a missing link
fgf21 is characterized as a systemic
enhancer of longevity it can be boosted
through prolonged fasting but thankfully
there are other less drastic measures
such as more carbs or
less protein
give people lots of starchy foods
and you can shoot up fgf21 levels the
healthiest sources would likely be whole
grains and beans since butyrate appears
to boost fgf21 too and we get that from
fiber that's one of the things our good
gut bugs make from fiber-rich foods
circulating after you have 21 levels are
also increased dramatically when you eat
a lower protein diet over 150 percent
increase within four weeks and when i
say protein restriction it can just be
restricting protein intake down from the
typical excess that most americans get
down to the recommended amount
the recommended daily allowance of
protein for most men is 56 grams of
protein a day though most american men
are getting over a hundred so if you
take men getting the typical excess of
about 112 grams a day and reduce them
down to 64
which again is still more than the
recommended 56 so the protein restricted
group was still getting more than enough
protein you can essentially double fgf21
levels in the blood
that may help explain why despite them
getting significantly more calories they
lost more body fat
how can you eat 300 more calories a day
and still lose two more pounds of
straight body fat by just bringing your
protein levels down to
normal levels right
who hasn't fantasized about a diet that
allows ingestion of excess calories that
are burned off effortlessly by
ramping up fat burning so you know maybe
we should play down protein to play up
metabolism thanks
to fgf21
even just a quite modest protein
restriction regimen down to the
recommended levels may have significant
clinical benefits
now this was after a month and a half a
similar study found that even less
protein restriction
taking men down to just 73 grams a day
resulted in a six-fold increase in fgf21
within a single week accompanied by a
significant increase in insulin
sensitivity they conclude
that dietary protein dilution
promotes metabolic health in humans
evidence suggesting that a lower protein
intake is positively associated with
increased health survival and insulin
sensitivity has continued to mount
but we weren't sure exactly how but
maybe fgf21 provides an explanation
interestingly studies were feeding
people nine percent calories from
protein which is about what the
okinawans were getting when they were
one of the healthiest longest living
populations in the world
you may remember my videos on methionine
restriction to both fight cancer and as
a life extension strategy methionine is
an amino acid found predominantly in the
animal proteins and so one could achieve
methionine restriction by you know
cutting down on animal foods well that
may actually be an fgf21 effect
methionine restriction boosts levels so
much so it's been called the most
important mediator of the metabolic
reprogramming and methionine
restrictions so
some proteins may be more important to
restrict than others
the highest methionine levels are in
meat legumes which are you know being
split peas chickpeas and lentils have
about three times less methionine than
meat
fgf21 has been proposed as a potential
mediator of the protection from cancer
autoimmune diseases obesity and diabetes
afforded by strictly plant-based diets
maybe that's one of the reasons that
whole food plant-based diets have been
shown to have such extraordinary results
yeah
take dr esselstyn's work for example
right showing that the number one killer
of men and women can be largely halted
or reversed and the risk of heart attack
almost eliminated with the help of a
whole food low-fat vegan diet
this benefit can't be attributed solely
to cholesterol reductions we have these
new powerful cholesterol-lowering drugs
now that can force cholesterol levels as
low as healthy eaters but appear to have
less effect so the market benefits
reported by esselstyn evidently reflect
a variety of protective mechanisms
associated with a whole food plant-based
diet and fgf21 may be one of those
mechanisms so it's not just the fat and
cholesterol but the quality and quantity
of protein that may also be playing a
role but there's never been a study to
see whether vegans do indeed have higher
levels of fgf21
until
now
i'm glad i didn't just pass on the study
based on the title
in addition to studying new zealand
obese mice they investigated the
circulating fgf21 levels among those
eating plant-based
and then put it to the test by removing
meat from other people's diets to see if
fgf21 would go up and
fgf21 levels were markedly higher in
vegan humans compared to omnivores and
they went up when the omnivores were
switched to vegetarian diets after just
four days
and not just a little fgf21 levels
increased by
232 percent before
and after
just four days free of meat
bottom line is that you know the various
fasting approaches are likely to have
limited efficacy particularly on aging
and conditions other than obesity unless
combined with high nourishment diets
such as the moderate calorie intake and
mostly plant-based mediterranean or
okinawa low protein diets by which they
mean the
recommended amount of protein
[Music]
you